## Prakul Sharma

Vancouver, BC, Canada (Willing to relocate)

+1 (236) 863-4883 • prakuls13@gmail.com • linkedin/sharmaprakul • github/prakulsharma • prakulsharma.github.io

## Profile -

Experienced Data Scientist with three years in advanced data analytics and AI-driven solutions. Applied machine learning to transform complex data into strategic insights and developed scalable AI/ML systems to drive data-centric initiatives. Seeking a challenging role to improve informed decision-making and promote collaborative success.

Work Experience -

## Graduate Research Assistant

Vancouver, Canada

Department of Sociology, UBC

December 2023 - Present

- Analyzed semantic evolution of the word "community" to identify 5+ significant shifts in its meaning over 10 decades.
- Employed topic modeling using **BERTopic**, coreference resolution, and NER using **spaCy** on over **50,000 news articles**.

#### **Data Scientist**

Bengaluru, India

SymphonyAI Industrial

October 2021 - July 2023

- $\bullet \ \ {\bf Spearheaded} \ \ {\bf anomaly} \ \ {\bf detection}, \ {\bf time-series} \ \ {\bf analysis}, \ {\bf and} \ \ {\bf predictive} \ \ {\bf modeling} \ \ {\bf projects} \ \ {\bf for} \ \ {\bf industrial} \ \ {\bf setups}.$
- Developed semi-supervised models for predicting motor equipment failure with 90%+ accuracy, yielding \$200k+ profit.
- ullet Implemented EHS incident forecasting models using PyTorch, achieving 80%+ accuracy using leading safety indicators.
- Created a no-code analytics interface using Dash, saving over 1200 man-hours annually.
- Formulated algorithms to extract 100+ features from high-frequency vibration data for anomaly detection modeling.

## DevOps/Software Engineer

Bengaluru, India

Infosys

- November 2020 October 2021
- $\bullet \ \, \text{Built MEAN-stack} \ \text{web application to automate VM life-cycle, saving 500+ man-hours} \ \text{yearly in resource management}.$
- $\bullet$  Automated user-specific software installation via UNIX scripts during VM creation, reducing setup time by 60%.
- Built scalable CI/CD pipelines using Azure DevOps Toolkit, ensuring efficient workflows in a cross-functional environment.
- Supervised and mentored 2 junior developers.

## - Projects -

## BCI: Quantitative Topic Modeling for Enhanced Stock Analysis

May 2024 - June 2024

- Automated parsing, transformation of 10-K filings into JSON files using regex, reducing data extraction time by half.
- Implemented topic data models using LDA, BERTopic and TopicGPT, achieving a 30% higher coherence score.
- Integrated Yahoo Finance API to add stock performance data, improving topic identification accuracy by 10%.

TextDetox

March 2024 – April 2024

- Developed multilingual detox models for 9 languages to enforce content moderation, using English as base.
- Built a translation-detoxify pipeline with NLLB-200 and used BART-base, T5-base as evaluation baselines.
- Fine-tuned Flan-T5 and TinyLlama on the Paradetox dataset, achieving 86%+ detoxification in texts.

#### ARCOT: Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus

February 2024 - March 2024

- Annotated 400 tasks for logical reasoning, enhancing LLM problem-solving with chain-of-thought prompting.
- Created Streamlit web app to visualize and search annotated tasks using cosine similarity.

#### - Education -

## Master of Data Science (Computational Linguistics)

Vancouver, Canada

The University of British Columbia

September 2023 – June 2024

- **GPA: 9.24**/10
- Coursework: Supervised & Unsupervised Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Data Structures & Algorithms, Databases & Data Retrieval, Data Visualization, Descriptive & Inferential Statistics, Feature Engineering

## Bachelor of Technology (Information Technology)

Delhi, India

Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University

August 2016 – July 2020

• **GPA: 8.91**/10

# - Skills ----

Machine Learning
Deep Learning
NLP
Data Science
Development
Database
Programming
Essential traits

Classification, Regression, Classification, Reinforcement Learning, Survival Analysis, Ensemble Models Neural Networks, Transformers, Autoencoders, CNNs, RNNs, LSTM, GANs, GNNs, Computer Vision GPT, BERT, spaCy, NLTK, Large language Models (LLMs), LangChain, RAG, Hugging Face, GenAI EDA, Statistical Analysis, Experimental Design, Power BI, Tableau, Data Wrangling, Predictive Modeling Software Life Cycle, Docker, CI/CD, FastAPI, Jenkins, Kubernetes, Agile, API, JIRA, Trello, Git, ETL SQL (PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQL Server), NoSQL (MongoDB), Spark, Snowflake, Azure, AWS, GCP Python (Pandas, NumPy, scikit-learn, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, OOP), R (Tidyverse), Java, Hadoop Collaboration, Adaptability, Problem-solving, Communication skills, Analytical, Leadership, Curiosity